Guide to the Gay Cable Network Archives, 1982-2001 MSS.231
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series X: Gay USA, 154212
  - 1991 Vol. IX, 246291
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 39 [Air date: 9/26/1991], September 1991; ID: 231.0317A; 154549 (Box 20, Media ID: 231.0317A)
      3. Interview with Tom Duane after his victory, including the controversy of him revealing his HIV positive status. Peter Valone is discussed.
      COMMERCIAL: American Life Resources
      4. ACT UP Demonstrates at Federal Plaza: Protesting lack of housing for people with AIDS. Protesters wear paper George Bush masks. Father Robert Castle of St. Mary's Episcopal Church is interviewed.
      COMMERCIAL: 970-BIG-1
      5. Panel on socialized medicine: Lou Maletta, Richard Martin, VP of Labour Congress in Canada, Dr. Haresh Kirpalani, Chris Axworthy of the Canadian Parliament.
      6. Lavender Health: Hadley Mays and Desiree Crump of the Koumbaya Gallery are interviewed. The first event at the gallery was broken up by the cops, and the chief of police refused to help. [Someone can be heard whistling in the background throughout the interview]
      7. Naming Names: Kirk-Evan Billet of GLAAD reports on Geraldo Rivera again. This time, Geraldo did a balanced, sympathetic show featuring William Kielly and Peggy Marlowe, and attended by members of the Pink Panthers. Kevin Barrell of the Gay and Lesbian Task Force was interviewed via satellite. Viewers are encouraged to write letters of appreciation to Geraldo Rivera.
      8. GCN Sports: Gutter George is under investigation for misappropriation of funds. The magazine Pediatrics publishes a report on what to do about HIV-positive athletes. COMMERCIAL: NAYA Natural Spring Water
      9. Lou Maletta announces the passing of David Gilbert, who set up a sort of refuge for southern gay men living in New York.
      [NOTE: The interview with Dr. Jeffery Lavigne does not occur in this episode.]
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 40 [Air date: 10/3/1991], October 1991; ID: 231.0318; 154550 (Box 20, Media ID: 231.0318)
      COMMERCIAL: National Coming Out Day, October 11
      1. California Governor Pete Wilson vetoes gay rights law that was passed by both houses of state legislature, leading to rioting. ACT UP in Washington DC protests AIDS policies of the federal government. Footage is shown of the protests. Several members are shown being arrested. Footage cuts to Universal Healthcare demonstration at the Capitol. Protesters march up the Capitol steps. Police are shown arresting protesters as other ACT UP members scream at them. ACT UP members are then shown INSIDE the Capitol, as police cuff scores of them.
      COMMERCIAL: Long Island Association for AIDS Care
      2. Chris Hennelly is interviewed about his legal battle against the police after he was brutally beaten and left with neurological damage. District Attorney Robert Morgenthau is pressing charges against Hennelly for resisting arrest. COMMERCIAL: American Life Resources
      3. The New York AIDS Coalition holds its fourth annual conference at the Mt. Sinai Medical Center. Ann Erickson speaks about redirecting funds to help fight the AIDS crisis and expand healthcare. David Hansell also speaks about expanding benefits for healthcare and getting more people on healthcare.
      COMMERCIAL: Resident Alien
      4. After the demise of OutWeek, NYQ hits newsstands. Troy Masters, co-publisher of NYQ is interviewed about the content and layout of the magazine, and the 18 columns that will rotate from week to week. Colleen Mangan is also interviewed, she is formerly from OutWeek. The importance of having both a male and female editor is emphasized, in order to keep a diverse amount of stories coming in.
      5. Northern Lights Alternatives reunion with Sally Fisher, which is a service agency for people with AIDS.
      COMMERCIAL: Help Stop The Violence
      6. Lavender Health: Part two of the interview with Hadley Mays and Desiree Crump of the Koumbaya Gallery. They are asked about what motivated the group. Part of the reason for opening the space was to create an alternative to the bar scene for gays and lesbians to meet.
      7. Naming Names: Dr. Henry Yeager of GLAAD discusses NBC's "Dear John", which portrays a financially-astute, mentally normal lesbian couple. Clips from the show are played. Viewers are asked to write letters of thanks to the producers of "Dear John".
      8. Andy Humm discusses how NBC cancels a planned episode of "Quantum Leap" about a suicidal gay teen.
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 40 [Air date: 10/3/1991], October 1991; ID: 231.0319; 154551 (Box 20, Media ID: 231.0319)
      [NOTE: This is the same episode as 0318.]
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 41 [Air date: 10/10/1991], October 1991; ID: 231.0320A; 155069 (Box 20, Media ID: 231.0320A)
      1. The Jeffery Hanlin case is discussed between Bill Dobbs and Andy Humm. A law in Michigan states that one must inform partner before having sex if they are HIV positive. Failure to do so can be tried as a felony. Dobbs discusses the 'spectacle' when Governer Cuomo extradited Hanlin to Michigan.
      2. Update on St. Patrick's Day Parade; Irish policemen bar gay and lesbians from marching in the parade. Carmine Red covers CUNY's First Lesbian and Gay Research Center inauguration. Cheryl Clarke and Martin Duberman speak. Alice Walker is interviewed.
      3. Human Rights Conference in Moscow, P-FLAGS. Footage is shown of demonstrators singing. Lou Maletta interviews Laurie Colburn, program director of P-FLAGS about her time in Russia. It took a great deal of negotiating and bribery to get a word processor and printer through for a Russian trying to print a gay-themed newsletter. A clip is shown of Colburn speaking on the steps of a government building.
      4. From Center Stage, Julie Wilson sings. Carmine Red interviews Ronald G. Cohn.
      5. Lou Maletta covers The '92 Desk Diary Benefiting D.I.F.F.A. and interviews John Hoffman about fundraisers and shows coming up.
      6. Lavender Health: Debra Fraser of the Black Leadership Commission on AIDS is interviewed about her organization and its advocacy and fundraising.
      7. Naming Names: Kirk-Evan Billet of GLAAD covers In Living Color and the new show Roc. Roc has a sympathetic and realistic portrayal of black gay men, while In Living Color used stereotypes. Viewers are encouraged to write to Fox in praise of Roc, but denouncing the "Men On" segments of In Living Color.
      8. GCN Sports: Prospect Park hosts the 2nd Annual Community Center Lesbian Softball Tournament, which raised over $3,000. The Magic Softball Tournament and the Women's Brooklyn FLAG Football League are covered.
      9. Lou Maletta interview the co-producers of Lookout: Lesbian and Gay Television Festival, Jean Carlomusto and Greg Borderwitz. The goal was to make a forum for television and video devoted to lesbians and gays. A clip from one film by Thomas Allen Harris, "Splash" is shown. A clip from "Bolo! Bolo!" which caused controversy in Toronto is shown. A daily ticket is only $8.
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 42 [Air date: 10/17/1991], October 1991; ID: 231.0321; 155070 (Box 21, Media ID: 231.0321)
      1. 2nd Annual Coming Out Day at the Gay and Lesbian Community Services Center.
      2. The Clarence Thomas-Anita Hill hearings are covered. Thomas is accused of homophobia by Andy Humm.
      3. Tom Smith is interviewed about the Wall Street Project, which is associated with the Coalition of Gay and Lesbian Rights. Nick Curto and Don Mitchell are also interviewed. Goal is to "put a gay and lesbian face on investment capital" Phone numbers for the Orientation for the Wall Street Project are displayed.
      4. Joyce Hunter, formerly of GCN and now the president of the National Lesbian and Gay Health Foundation is interviewed.
      5. The Identity House's Laughing Out Proud 25th Anniversary program is covered. Jeanne Nicolosi is interviewed. The Wiseguys and Harvey Firestien are performing. Ticket information is displayed.
      6. At a benefit for Housing Works, Keith D. Cylar is interviewed about Housing Works. Phillipe Brooke is interviewed about his photography show, Living With AIDS: Embracing the Light.
      7. Quentin Crisp, the subject of Resident Alien is interviewed. The film is about Crisp and his status, and his views on America.
      8. GCN Sports: Rich Flowers interviews Cheryl Embry and Tania Ingraham, two organizers of Gay Games '94.
      9. Lavender Health: Sean Dwyer of Gay and Lesbian People of Color holds a conference to "sensitize AIDS service providers to the needs of the Gay and Lesbian client of color".
      10. Naming Names: Cheryl Moch of GLAAD covers the Pentagon releasing a report that states gays and lesbians do not pose a threat because of their sexual orientation. This is at the time when gays and lesbians are being expelled from the military. Viewers are encouraged to write to Dick Cheney at the Department of Defense.
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 43 [Air date: 10/24/1991], October 1991; ID: 231.0322; 155071 (Box 21, Media ID: 231.0322)
      1. Andy Humm interviews Lance Ringel, who just became Assistant Commissioner of Human Rights and works closely with Governor Cuomo. They discuss his successor issuing a ruling that ROTC couldn't have recruiters on campus (which was discussed in an earlier episode). Humm asks if there's any plan to ban Boy Scouts of America from using state buildings due to their anti-gay bias, to which Ringel replies no.
      COMMERCIAL: Christopher Street Book Store
      2. Interview with Sandy Rapp, author of God's Country: A Case Against Theocracy. Rapp discusses religious fundamentalists and their anti-gay agenda. COMMERCIAL: The Monster
      3. Lou Maletta interviews Alain Montour, director of Parents and Friends of Lesibans and Gays (PFLAG) NY, who is holding the 11th annual awards dinner dance to honor Ruth Messinger and Andy Humm.
      4. Between the Covers: Rich Flowers interviews Tom Spanbauer, author of The Man Who Fell in Love With the Moon. One point of discussion is the upcoming 500th anniversary of Columbus' landing and how he treated Native Americans.
      COMMERCIAL: The Human Rights Campaign Fund 10th Anniversary at the Rainbow Room
      5. GCN Sports: 1991 Soccer Nationals. Tania Ingrham is interviewed about the 1994 New York games.
      6. A bumper/clip not given any context showing Lou Maletta and two other men dancing through a hiking trail.
      7. Lou Maletta interviews David Deveraux, who has created a calendar to raise money for the AIDS Emergency Fund in San Francisco.
      8. Another bumper/clip of Lou Maletta and another man, again on the trail from earlier.
      9. Lavender Health: Debra Fraser-Howze, executive director of BLCA is interviewed.
      10. Another bumper/clip of Lou Maletta and co. hiking.
      COMMERCIAL: AIDS Dance-a-Thon
      11. Naming Names: Scott Sherman of GLAAD discusses Scholastic on Target, a magazine distributed to high schools that runs a positive story on gay and lesbian relationships. Viewers are encouraged to write positive letters to Scholastic.
      12. Another clip/bumper.
      13. Lou Maletta interviews Sam Abdul, organizer of 'Stripping for AIDS at Star Sapphire', which is an AIDS benefit in the form of a 'strip-a-thon'.
      The credits roll over more footage of Maletta and co. hiking.
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 44 [Air date: 10/31/1991], October 1991; ID: 231.0323; 155072 (Box 21, Media ID: 231.0323)
      1. An update on the Human Rights Commission confronting the organizers of the St. Patrick's Day parade. Interview with Evan Wolfson, an attorney who took on the Julio Rivera case.
      COMMERCIAL: GAYNET
      3. City Council Candidates Seek Gay and Lesbian Support: Charles Millard (a Republican) and Carol Greitzer (a Democrat) state their positions on gay rights. Andy Humm interviews Traci Alexander after the speeches.
      4. Liz Holtzman, city comptroller, is interviewed about the Julio Rivera case, in which the prosecutor wanted to ask jurors about their sexual orientation. COMMERCIAL: Outrageous Desire, an art exhibit.
      5. Robert Abrams, New York State Attorney General talks about his desire to run for Senate and bring the gay rights struggle to Washington. Joyce Hunter and Sandy Lowe are also interviewed.
      6. Lou Maletta interviews James Turanski, director of the Together Program at Regent Hospital, a program that addresses the enormous problem of drug addiction amongst gays and lesbians. Footage is shown of the ribbon-cutting ceremony of the program, with a speech by Marjorie Hill. Lou Maletta then interviews Dr. Cathy Gordon.
      7. Century Plaza Demonstration. Gay and lesbian activists protest the veto by Pete Wilson of the gay rights bill. Protesters are violently dragged through the streets by police.
      8. Lou Maletta interviews Mark Epstein and Michele D'ermo, organizers of the 10th Human Rights Campaign Fund.
      COMMERCIAL: Regent Hospital's Together Program.
      9. Lavender Health: Part two of the interview with Debra Fraser-Howze, executive director of BLCA.
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 45 [Air date: 11/7/1991], November 1991; ID: 231.0324; 155073 (Box 21, Media ID: 231.0324)
      1. A few New York Times stories are covered. Footage from Election Day and an interview with Tom Duane.
      2. Update on the Julio Rivera case. Interviews with Ted Rivera, Julio's brother, Peg Rivera, Julio's sister-in-law, and David Kirshenbaum of the Gay and Lesbian Anti-Violence Project.
      COMMERCIAL: NYQ Magazine
      3. Jimmy Somerville: A Benefit Concert for ACT-UP
      COMMERCIAL: 970 BIG-1
      4. Interview with Rodger McFarland. McFarland outed Tom Duane but didn't out Brad Davis, actor and star of "Midnight Express", who had recently died of AIDS. McFarland is asked bluntly why he outed Duane's HIV-positive status.
      5. Tim McFeely of the Human Rights Campaign Fund is interviewed about government policy that could help gays and lesbians. The Clarence Thomas hearings are discussed, as is campaign finance.
      6. GCN Sports: Plug for the Fundraiser for Gay Games IV. Footage is shown of a marathon.
      7. Lavender Health: Blades for AIDS, a Northern Lights Alternative program run by Michael Fairman and Ron Nieberding. Celebrity roller disco skating.
      8. Naming Names: Ellen Carton covers gay-positive episodes of LA Law. Viewers are encouraged to write to the producers of LA Law.
      COMMERCIAL: 970-BIG1
      9. Alan Bonicatti signs books to raise money for the Hektrik-Martin Institute. Bonicatti is interviewed by Lou Maletta.
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 46 [Air date: 11/14/1991], November 1991; ID: 231.0325A; 155074 (Box 21, Media ID: 231.0325A)
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 46, 1991; ID: 231.0326; 155075 (Box 21, Media ID: 231.0326)
      NOTE: This episode is mostly a repeat of 231 0325A. Exceptions are marked with an asterisk.
      COMMERCIAL: Naya Spring Water
      1. Lou Maletta and Carmine Red report from NGLTF: Creating Change 1991 in Virginia. Urvashi Vaid, Maruice Solis-Marich, Tom Stoddard of the Lambda Legal Defense, give speeches. 'Magic' Johnson revealing his HIV-positive status is mentioned. Lou Maletta narrates over other speeches. Lisa Power, co-chair of ILGA in England, Leonid Frolov from Russia, and 'D' Cameron, Mr. Leather 1991 are interviewed.
      *2. UCLA protest against governor Pete Wilson, who struck down a gay rights law. Ed Anderson covers the story. A speech by Pete Wilson is interrupted by protesters, who pack the stands.
      COMMERCIAL: My Own Private Idaho
      3. Veteran's Day march protesting the exclusion of gays and lesbians from the military at the Pentagon. Greg Scott speaks of being expelled from the NAVY.
      4. Ornan Yekutieli, the deputy mayor of Jerusalem, and member of the Human Rights Party is interviewed.
      5. A brief speech by Andrew Stien in support of the domestic partnership bill.
      6. GLAAD declares a 'Trojan war' against condom manufacturer Carter-Wallace. Ellen Carton and Scott Sherman condemn the lack of support for gays the company is showing.
      7. GCN Sports: Special spotlight version, about Magic Johnson's HIV-positive status.
      8. ACT UP protests Bush's visit to NYC by demonstrating at the Waldorf-Astoria.
      9. Naming Names: Cheryl Moch covers Connie Chung's story on women being thrown out of the military for not hooking up with superior officers. Viewers are encouraged to write to CNN.
      COMMERCIAL: Regent Hospital's Together Program. 10. Lavender Health: Blades for AIDS, a Northern Lights Alternative program run by Michael Fairman and Ron Nieberding. Celebrity roller disco skating. This previously appeared on 0324.
      11. Edward Maloney from the Out of the Closet Thrift Shop asks for volunteers.
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 47 [Air date: 11/21/1991], November 1991; ID: 231.0327; 155076 (Box 21, Media ID: 231.0327)
      1. Lee Sharmat and Andy Humm cover the Magic Johnson story. Update on Julio Rivera. Delta Airlines asks employees illegal, probing questions.
      2. Human Rights Campaign Celebrates its 10th Anniversary at the Rainbow Room. Harvey Firestein speaks.
      3. Controversy about using undercover cops to pose as gays in areas where gay bashings happen. Thusfar, no arrests. Joe Nicholson of the New York Post (who broke the story), Bill Dobbs, and David Kirschenbaum are interviewed.
      COMMERICAL: The Monster
      4. Paul E. Tsnognas speaks to a group about gay rights. Lou Maletta interviews him after the speech.
      5. UCLA protest against governor Pete Wilson, who struck down a gay rights law. Ed Anderson covers the story. A speech by Pete Wilson is interrupted by protesters, who pack the stands. Repeat of segment from 231 0326.
      6. Deep Dish with D. Isidore: Neo Nakamura faces immigration issues. Judy Rome, a parking lot magnate, tries to get rid of a classic building. Isidore repeatedly refers to River Phoenix as 'River Penis' repeatedly and insinuates that he's gay.
      7. GCN Sports: HIV testing for boxers is covered. Women Athletes of New York's Volleyball season starts. Laura Moore, an ice skater, is interviewed.
      8. Leo de Kam of HIV-WIJZER in Amsterdam is interviewed.
      9. Lavender Health: Ellen Saltzberg interviews Dr. Marjorie Hill. Same interview as 325.
      10. Naming Names: Kirk-Evan Billet covers the talk show "9 Broadcast Plaza" which took up the position that heterosexuals can be 'turned' gay. Viewers are encouraged to write to Michael B. Alexander of WWOR-TV.
      11. The murderers of Julio Rivera are found guilty.
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 48 [Air date: 11/28/1991], November 1991; ID: 231.0328; 155077 (Box 21, Media ID: 231.0328)
      1. Julio Rivera case. Andrew Jacobs of NYQ, who was in the courtroom covering the trial, is interviewed. Jay Blocher reports from Queens as a demonstration takes place. Peg Rivera, Julio's sister-in-law is interview.
      2. Andy Humm and Lou Maletta discuss Chris Hennelly and police brutality. Liz Garro and Dennis DeLeon are interviewed.
      3. Geraldine Ferraro is interviewed about her candidacy for the US Senate.
      COMMERCIAL: Cupid's Treasures
      4. Day Without Art: Event held on World AIDS Day, December 1, to commemorate those who have died of HIV and AIDS. Patrick O'Connell is interviewed. Museums across Manhattan will replace pieces by gay artists with a block of text about AIDS to raise awareness.
      5. Gay Men's Health Crisis distributes thousands of condoms. Brooklyn high school students (with the help of ACT UP) stage a sit-in at the office of Irene Impellizzeri, who opposed condom distribution in public schools. 10 are arrested for trespassing.
      6. PFLAG 11th annual dinner and dance, honoring Ruth Messinger and Andy Humm. Humm's parents are in attendance.
      7. The death of Freddie Mercury is mentioned. A commercial for Ads Against Aids: People Taking Action Against AIDS is shown.
      8. Alternatives to AZT: Bob Lederer of ACT UP talks about alternative treatments to HIV and AIDS. Deborah Gamble and Dr. Bernard Behari are interviewed.
      9. John Scagliotti is interviwed about his event Out of Our Trunks, which is taking place at the Limelight.
      10. Naming Names: Joe Windish of GLAAD talks about TV Guide's repeated exclusion of gay and lesbian programming, including GCN. Viewers are encouraged to write to TV Guide to demand they include GCN.
      COMMERCIAL: SF AIDS Foundation (opera singer)
      11. Lavender Health: Margret Redfield is interviewed about AIDS prevention and needle exchanges.
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 49 [Air date: 12/5/1991], December 1991; ID: 231.0329; 155078 (Box 21, Media ID: 231.0329)
      COMMERICAL: Christopher Street Bookstore
      1. Cardinal O'Connor makes more homophobic statements. GMHC's Dance-a-Thon. Event raised $1.6 million.
      2. A Day Without Art – The Studio Museum in Harlem. Ruth Messinger speaks. Joel Motley, museum chairman, is interviewed. Mayor David Dinkins speaks. Museum of Modern Art: Agnes Gund is interviewed. The New Museum: Robert Blanchon speaks about the exhibits. The Whitney is also shown. A performance by Assoto Saint is shown.
      3. Footage from Night Without Light.
      COMMERCIAL: Gods Love We Deliver
      4. ACT UP protests NYC's TB policies.
      5. Andy Humm announces that the World Health Organization stated that in 8 years, 30-40 million HIV infections, and 12-18 million full-blown AIDS cases. Ingar Bruggemann, Rafeeuddin Ahmed, Luis Maria Gomez, Dr. Daniel H. Merson, and James Boliba Baba, speak at the UN about the AIDS crisis.
      6. Lavender Health: Part two of Margret Redfield interview.
      7. Naming Names: Dr. Henry Yeager of GLAAD follows up on Cracker Barrel firing all gay employees, 20/20 covered the story in a way that was positive to gays and lesbians, and criticized Cracker Barrel. A few clips from the 20/20 piece are shown. Viewers are encouraged to write to ABC.
      8. GCN Sports: Magic Johnson is discussed. Duke Bluedevil's player Christian Laytner comes out.
      9. Footage from World AIDS Day is shown after the credits.
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 49, Atlanta, Georgia, 1991; ID: 231.0330; 155079 (Box 21, Media ID: 231.0330)
      Same as 0329, but with some different commercials, and further scenes from World AIDS Day featured over the credits, plus a COMMERCIAL for World AIDS Day, and a McGruff the Crime Dog COMMERCIAL
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 50 [Air date: 12/12/1991], December 1991; ID: 231.0331; 155080 (Box 21, Media ID: 231.0331)
      1. The death of a Florida woman who was accidentially infected with AIDS by her dentist is covered, as is the 2nd anniversary of the mass protest.
      2. Lou Maletta interviews Senate candidate Elizabeth Holtzman. She discusses the need for a senate that will address the financial crisis, and how the Anita Hill hearings prompted her to run.
      2. Lou Maletta at the Gay and Lesbian Community Center for an exhibit called 'Graphic Facts', PSA posters about AIDS.
      3. Chris McManus reports from God's Love We Deliver; a charity group that gives gourmet meals to AIDS patients. Cleo's of 9th Avenue is also covered. Viewers are encouraged to volunteer.
      4. Between the Covers: Interviewing Bruce Nussbam, author of Good Intentions. The book is about medical companies withholding AIDS medicine. The book goes into the rise of the 'buyer's clubs' and ACT UP.
      5. Lou Maletta expresses his disappointment with Ads Against AIDS. Some of the TV ads from the group are shown. Maletta then goes over some news items, including Chris Hennelly's case still in doubt, and Joe Stephan being expelled from the Air Force.
      COMMERCIAL: SF AIDS Foundation (arm wrestling)